Okay, next section, inflammatory conditions.
The first disorder is called acute mastitis.
Now, to understand this, let's just go back
to the whiteboard for a minute.
So here's the surface of the skin of the breast,
and let's pretend that this is a large duct
coming out into the nipple,
and in this particular case,
you've got a woman who's breastfeeding.
Now, when she breastfeeds,
there's stress placed on the skin here,
and when there's stress placed on the skin,
that can result in fissures or disruption of the skin,
which then allows for entry of staph aureus.
When staph aureus comes into the breast,
it will then result in acute mastitis.
So again, acute mastitis is bacterial infection of the breast,
usually due to staph aureus,
and it's associated with breastfeeding.
Now, what's the presentation?
Well, of course, the patient's gonna have
an infection of the breast,
and so there'll be a warm erythematous breast.
There may be a purulent nipple discharge.
Let's say that pus begins to come out of the nipple.
That would result in a purulent nipple discharge.
Now, the treatment would be twofold.
Number one, continued drainage.
So, although it's awkward, if the woman was breastfeeding,
she would continue to feed the child.
And then number two, you wanna give antibiotics
to disrupt the staph aureus,
and a classic drug that would be used in this circumstance
would be dicloxacillin.
So let's go back now and read the text.
So what do I say?
Acute mastitis, bacterial infection of the breast,
staph aureus, breastfeeding.
And then I say that the presentation is a warm erythematous breast
with a purulent nipple discharge.
And again, the treatment drainage and antibiotics
such as dicloxacillin.
So those are all the high yields.
Important to note that this particular disorder
can progress to formation of an abscess,
a walled-off area of inflammation.
And so that could then result in a mass.
So in some patients with this type of presentation,
you may also feel a little bit of a mass.
And of course, that would be due to an abscess.
The next disorder is perioductal mastitis,
and this is inflammation of the subareolar ducts.
Let's go to the whiteboard for a minute
and do a little normal,
and then this disorder becomes very straightforward.
So here's the skin of the breast,
and here's a large subareolar duct.
Let's remind ourselves that this large subareolar duct
is lined by epithelial cells, which are columnar.
So these are columnar epithelial cells,
and underneath that are these myoepithelial cells,
of course, that's the normal.
Now, I want to remind you that when you look
at the lactiferous duct,
the ducts that are just going into the nipple,
the epithelium here of the lactiferous ducts
is a highly specialized epithelium.
And remember from chapter one
that highly specialized epithelia,
they require vitamin A in order to maintain themselves,
so that this epithelium here
is highly dependent on vitamin A.
Now, if a patient smokes,
and this disorder is predominantly seen in smokers,
by the way, if a patient smokes,
they get a relative vitamin A deficiency,
and when they get a relative vitamin A deficiency,
they lose the ability to maintain
this specialized epithelium,
so that this epithelium now becomes squamous.
And as it becomes squamous,
you get this squamous metaplasia
that occurs here in the lactiferous ducts,
and that then would produce some degree of keratin,
which would plug these ducts.
Now, when this duct gets plugged,
you've blocked a tube,
and there's a general principle in pathology
that any time you block a tube,
you're gonna get inflammation behind that block.
So now these patients get inflammation behind the duct,
and that then is called perioductal mastitis.
Now, what are some of the consequences of this inflammation?
Well, first of all,
you're gonna have this big area of inflammation
with some healing and some fibrosis,
so it's gonna feel like a mass in the subareolar region,
and so it's gonna present as a subareolar mass.
The second thing that's gonna happen
is with all of this inflammation,
you're gonna get some fibrosis as part of the healing response,
and that fibrosis is going to arise
through granulation tissue, of course,
and you know that granulation tissue
contains myofibroblasts,
and so myofibroblasts are gonna contract,
and they're gonna pull in the skin
right in the area of the nipple,
and as they pull in the tissue in the skin
by their contraction,
they're gonna cause nipple retraction,
and so these patients can also have nipple retraction.
Now, with that as a background,
let's go back and read what I say in the book.
So, I say that perioductal mastitis
is inflammation of the subareolar ducts,
usually seen in smokers,
I've already explained that,
again, because of a relative vitamin A deficiency,
and it classically presents
as a subareolar mass with nipple retraction.
Now, this nipple retraction is important
because I think, from my experience with medical students,
when they hear the word nipple retraction,
they automatically think breast cancer.
However, that's not always the case.
You can have nipple retraction with, for example,
an inflammatory condition such as perioductal mastitis.
The next disorder is called mammary duct ectasia,
and the idea here is, again, go back to the whiteboard,
here's the skin, and then you've got this normal duct,
and you get inflammation of the duct,
and when you get inflammation of the duct,
you get some dilatation of that duct.
That's called mammary duct ectasia.
Now, as you get dilatation of the duct,
all the inflammatory debris
is gonna be piling up within that duct,
and some of that inflammatory debris
will come out of the nipple,
giving what is classically seen in this particular disorder
of a green-brown nipple discharge, very high yield.
Green-brown nipple discharge.
And that is basically the idea of mammary duct ectasia.
Inflammation of the wall of the subareolar duct,
which then results in ectasia, or dilatation, of that duct,
and then, of course, that then is gonna result in
this green-brown nipple discharge coming out of the duct.
Of course, at the same time, because you've got inflammation,
you might feel a little bit of a mass.
So let's go now and read what I say in the book.
So I say mammary duct ectasia is inflammation
with dilatation of the subareolar ducts.
It's relatively rare.
It classically arises in multiparous postmenopausal women.
Now, this is very important.
The classic history on an examination would be
that you would have a multiparous woman,
but I want to highlight here that this is a mass, right,
because it's gonna form a mass because of the inflammation.
This is a mass in a postmenopausal woman.
Generally speaking, when we think about masses
in postmenopausal women, we're very worried about cancer.
And that's because breast cancer is predominantly a disease
of postmenopausal women.
And so don't, so again, this is the general principle
that yes, breast cancer normally occurs
in postmenopausal women, but again, you should remember
that not every mass in a postmenopausal woman
is a breast cancer.
And so this is another example where examiners like to try
to make you think that they're dealing with breast cancer,
but you're not dealing with breast cancer,
you're dealing with mammary duct ductasia.
And what's gonna give that away
is this green-brown nipple discharge.
That's super high yield.
If you've got green-brown nipple discharge,
it's highly suggestive of mammary duct ductasia.
Now, of course, if you were worried,
and in particular because this is a postmenopausal woman,
you might be worried, so you'd do a biopsy.
And when you do a biopsy, you'll see chronic inflammation
of the plasma cells, and the plasma cells are characteristic
as well of this disorder.
The last of the inflammatory disorders is fat necrosis.
This is where you get necrosis of the breast fat.
Now, remember from chapter one of our texts
that when you get fat necrosis, there's two ways.
You can have enzymatic digestion of the fat,
for example, as occurs with the peripancreatic fat
in pancreatitis, or you can have trauma-related disruption
of the fat, and so in fat necrosis of the breast,
it's usually related to trauma.
Now, why is this important?
Because it can present in two ways.
It can present as a mass, so for example,
either the woman feels the mass,
or the physician feels the mass,
and that's because fat necrosis was going to result
in disruption of the fat, and some fibrosis,
and some giant cell reaction, and some inflammation,
which could then form a mass.
But perhaps even more classic, and particularly high yield,
is that it can also result in calcification on mammogram.
The idea, again, is that when you have fat necrosis,
you get saponification.
Then saponification is the addition of calcium
to that fat necrosis, and when a woman goes for mammogram,
they'll detect the calcifications,
and recall that calcifications are one way
by which we screen for breast cancer.
So it could produce calcifications,
which would then require, in certain cases, a biopsy.
And if a biopsy were to be performed,
we would see necrotic fat with associated calcifications,
because of the quote-unquote saponification,
and then the presence of giant cells as well.
And that's the classic finding in fat necrosis.
Now, I'll just remind you, especially on examinations,
they don't usually tell you that there's a history of trauma.
In fact, even clinically, most women will not come and say,
oh yeah, I had this trauma.
They don't recognize that they had trauma.
For example, a woman plays softball
and gets hit with a softball in the chest.
She wouldn't necessarily call that trauma,
but that might be sufficient trauma
to actually result in fat necrosis.
And so when I say trauma,
it doesn't need to be a major form of trauma.
It could be anything that could damage the fat
of the breast parenchyma.
And so that closes off our section
on inflammatory disorders.